חגיגה. Hagiga.
Alright, I have the זכות zechut to start מסכת חגיגה Masechet Hagiga
with
you.
Good point.
חגי Haggai named has to do חגיגה. Hagiga. For those of you
who I haven't met, which I think is nobody, I'm Haggai Reznikoff,
Rabbi Haggai Reznikoff, and I'm just filling in for Rabbi Linzer today.
Just to remind me what's my mandate? What time do we have?
8:30. 8:30, okay.
What I'd like to do is just go over, I want to
start with the דף daf to make sure we get through the
דף. daf. Once we've, once I'm sure we're through the דף, daf,
then I'll go back and talk just about a broader introduction to
מסכת חגיגה. Masechet Hagiga. But let's just start with the דף. daf.
הכל חייבין בראיה, Hakol chayavin bere'iyah, the משנה Mishna says. There are
three קרבנות korbanot that you bring to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
during a חג. chag. You bring during a מועד, moed, one of
the שלוש רגלים. shalosh regalim. You bring a קרבן ראיה, korban re'iyah,
that's an עולה, olah, a קרבן korban that's going to be burned
up, and you bring that just for coming and being seen. It's
a show-up קרבן. korban. You bring קרבנות חגיגה, korbanot chagiga, which is
a sacrifice for the holiday, and you bring קרבנות שמחה. korbanot simcha.
You bring קרבנות korbanot in order to be משמח, mesameach, and the
last two are קרבנות שלמים, korbanot shelamim, which are קרבנות korbanot that
you eat, as opposed to the first one which is an עולה,
olah, which you don't eat, you burn up entirely.
הכל חייבין בראיה, Hakol chayavin bere'iyah, says the משנה. Mishna. Everybody is
required to bring the first, a קרבן ראיה. korban re'iyah. We haven't
heard anything about the others.
חוץ מחרש שוטה וקטן, Chutz mecheireish shoteh vekattan, except for a deaf
person, a person who is not
cognitively... what's a medical term for it today?
What's the word for somebody who is considered to be... they have
to have agency... competence? Right, competency. So a שוטה shoteh is somebody
who's not competent, and a קטן, kattan, a minor.
וטומטום, Vetumtum, and somebody whose gender is undetermined. ואנדרוגינוס, Ve'androginos,
or somebody who has both sets of genitalia, somebody who is... it's
not that they're undetermined, but rather that they are both male and
female.
ונשים, Venashim,
and women. ועבדים שאינם משוחררים, Ve'avadim she'einam meshuchararim, and slaves who have
not yet been freed. That language in the משנה Mishna is interesting
language, because generally in the הלכה halakha we say that slaves who
have been freed are not slaves in any sense anymore, they're converts.
But slaves who have not yet been freed, says the
משנה.
Mishna. Is this עבדים
עברים
avadim
ivrim
or עבדים כנענים? avadim kena'anim?
My expectation is עבדים כנענים. avadim kena'anim.
In general, yeah, it's so interesting that there would even be a
הוה אמינא hava amina that כנעני kena'ani somehow would have a חיוב.
chiyuv.
Well, I mean, remember that an עבד כנעני eved kena'ani is
פטור ממצוות עשה שהזמן גרמה, pattur mimitzvot asei shehazeman gerama, from non-time-bound
positive מצוות, mitzvot, but is... has all the other מצוות, mitzvot, has
to follow all the prohibitions and so on. So
it is certainly interesting, but it's not inconsistent with our general sort
of שיטה shita on slaves.
החיגר, Hechigeir, somebody who is lame. והסומא, Vehasuma, somebody who's blind. And
we'll see, as it'll be by the end of this דף daf
and the beginning of the next, the question of disabilities and people
who have disabilities and how do they fit in. We've talked about
a deaf person, now we've talked about somebody who's lame and somebody
who's blind, and how exactly do they fit in this. והחולה, Vehacholeh,
somebody who's sick doesn't have to bring a ראיה. re'iyah.
והזקן, Vehazaken,
and somebody who's too old.
Question: what does that mean, too old? ומי שאינו יכול לעלות ברגליו,
Umi she'eino yachol la'alot beraglav, and somebody who is not able to
walk for whatever reason on their own.
איזהו קטן? Eizehu kattan? Yes, David? The...
it's David, right?
That's David, you're Charlie. Sorry.
Some of these folks are actually obligated in הקהל, Hakhel, even though
it's a time-bound positive commandment that is very similar to ascending for
the שלוש רגלים. shalosh regalim.
Yes, but this so this is ראייה, re'iya, this has a this
is related to a very specific פסוק pasuk that we'll see in
the in the גמרא, Gemara,
and that פסוק pasuk is going to determine who these people are,
and there is going to be a comparison to הקהל. Hakhel. I
don't think we're going to get to it today, but it will
be it will be part of the discussion.
איזהו קטן Eizehu katan asks the משנה, Mishna, what kind of a
minor are we talking about? כל שאינו יכול לרכב על כתפיו של
אביו ולעלות מירושלים להר הבית דברי בית שמאי. Kol she'eino yachol lirkov
al ktefav shel aviv v'la'alot miYerushalayim l'Har HaBayit divrei Beit Shammai. בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says anybody who is too little to be able
to ride on his father's shoulders or her father's shoulders, well presumably
we're talking about the male children, but to ride on his father's
shoulders and go from Jerusalem to הר הבית. Har HaBayit. Interesting that
those are considered to be two separate locations. Yes.
ובית הלל אומרים, U'Beit Hillel omrim, בית הלל Beit Hillel have a
different position. כל שאינו יכול לאחוז בידו של אביו ולעלות מירושלים להר
הבית שנאמר שלוש רגלים. Kol she'eino yachol l'echoz b'yado shel aviv v'la'alot
miYerushalayim l'Har HaBayit she'ne'emar shalosh regalim.
בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's anybody who can't hold his father's
hand but walk from Jerusalem to הר הבית Har HaBayit on his
own two feet.
Who's older? Well,
what קטן katan are we talking about? Who says who says the
קטן katan needs to be older in order to be חייב chayav
in in ראייה? re'iya?
בית הלל Beit Hillel would seem to be.
בית הלל'ס. Beit Hillel's. בית הלל'ס Beit Hillel's child is older, right?
Because he's the one who you need to be able to walk
all the way from wherever they start to הר הבית. Har HaBayit.
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says as long as he can as long
as he can ride on his father's shoulders.
And I'll just point out that there's no there's not a general
כלל, klal, but we often expect בית הלל Beit Hillel to be
more מיקל meikel than בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Here it seems like
בית שמאי Beit Shammai is sort of more wide-reaching in terms of,
oh, I want more children to be חייב, chayav, but of course
חיוב chiyuv is a is a חומרא, chumra, חיוב chiyuv is not
a קולא. kulla. So in this case, בית הלל Beit Hillel or
actually are actually less strict. בית שמאי Beit Shammai are more strict
because they include more children in the grouping who have to go
to give the קרבן ראייה. korban re'iya. Charlie?
They have the language מירושלים להר הבית miYerushalayim l'Har HaBayit implying that
הר הבית Har HaBayit is not part of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Yes, that that is an interesting thing. I'm not sure exactly what
to say about that.
And the reason בית הלל Beit Hillel says that it has to
be a child who can walk to הר הבית Har HaBayit is
that it says שלוש רגלים. shalosh regalim. And רש"י Rashi says it
means that you should be able to לעלות ברגל, la'alot b'regel, you
should be actually be able to go on your own two feet.
בית שמאי אומרים הראייה שתי כסף והחגיגה מעה כסף. Beit Shammai omrim
ha're'iya shtei kesef v'hachagiga ma'ah kesef. בית שמאי Beit Shammai say that
the עולה, olah, the price that you pay for this particular קרבן
korban is two pieces of silver and the חגיגה, chagiga, the other
sacrifice is a single silver coin. ובית הלל אומרים הראייה מעה כסף
והחגיגה שתי כסף. U'Beit Hillel omrim ha're'iya ma'ah kesef v'hachagiga shtei kesef.
בית הלל Beit Hillel say the opposite, that the ראייה, re'iya, the
one that you burn up is one coin and the and the
חגיגה chagiga is two. And I'll just point out again,
it seems that בית הלל'ס Beit Hillel's more מיקל meikel in this
position because what do you do with the חגיגה? chagiga?
You eat it, right? So if you spend more money on the
one you're going to eat, you get more benefit out of you
get more bang for your buck, as it were.
The גמרא Gemara says
הכל לאתויי מאי? Hakol l'aituyei mai?
There's a position in the גמרא Gemara that says that when you
use general languages like זה הכלל zeh haklal or הכל, hakol, it's
not just to tell you everyone, it's to tell you someone who
you thought wouldn't be included is actually included in this list. And
then the גמרא Gemara tries to figure out who could it be.
So who's being added here?
לאתויי מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין. L'aituyei mi she'chetzyo eved v'chetzyo
ben chorin. The גמרא Gemara answers maybe it's to include somebody who
is half a slave and half free. How do you get someone
who's half a slave and half free?
That's correct, you buy you get together with somebody, pool your funds,
buy a slave, and then one of them gets an attack of
conscience or something and says you know what? My half is free.
Not really time, but I'll just point out that Puddin'head Wilson was
called Puddin'head because of the joke that he made where he said
there was a dog barking and he said I wish I owned
half that dog, and somebody said why do you wish you owned
half? And he said well I would shoot my half.
And they said oh, sounds like a regular Puddin'head. And that's how
he got that name. But that's מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין
mi she'chetzyo eved v'chetzyo ben chorin that you buy in. in half
and then one side frees him. So you might think that because
he's half a slave, he should, he doesn't have to
go to הר הבית. Har HaBayit. And the answer is no, he's
partly free, and that means that he does have to bring this
קרבן. korban.
But nobody ever agrees on anything in the גמרא. Gemara. So we
say ולרבינא דאמר מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין פטור. u'leRavina de'amar
mi she'chetzyo eved ve'chetzyo ben chorin patur. Ravina has an expressed position
that this person who's half a slave and half free does not
have to bring this קרבן ראייה. korban re'iyah. So how does Ravina
read our משנה? Mishna? How does he solve that problem?
פטור מן הראייה. patur min ha're'iyah. הכל לאתויי מאי? hakol l'atuyei mai?
Back to our original question, what does this include?
לאתויי חיגר ביום ראשון ונתפשט ביום שני. l'atuyei chiger b'yom rishon v'nitpashet
b'yom sheni. It is to include somebody who on the first day
of חג chag was lame, but by the second day had healed
and was able to walk again.
That's the, that's who you might think because he was lame, lame
people are excluded from this, and we, but he because he heals
in time for to still be in the holiday, we call that,
we say that he's still חייב. chayav.
But of course, that's not going to be good enough either, because
there's another position that makes a problem. הניחא למאן דאמר כולן תשלומין
זה לזה. ha nicha l'man d'amar kulan tashlumin zeh lazeh.
There is two positions in the גמרא. Gemara. One says that
you have to bring this קרבן, korban, קרבן ראייה korban re'iyah and
various other קרבנות korbanot over the course of seven days if you
go on סוכות, Sukkot, seven days on פסח Pesach and so on.
You have to bring these קרבנות korbanot a certain number over the
course of seven. And if you bring, if you missed one day,
then you bring one on the next day. But it's not a,
there's no particular קרבן korban for any particular day. And therefore, that
makes sense, according to this position,
that somebody who was lame on the first day can bring it
on the second day, or rather is still required to bring it
on the second day. But there's another position. אלא למאן דאמר כולן
תשלומין לראשון. ela l'man d'amar kulan tashlumin l'rishon.
What about the position who says actually your חיוב, chiyuv, your requirement
to bring the קרבן korban is only on the first day? If
it's only on the first day, then if you have something that
makes you not חייב chayav on the first day, you don't have
any requirement to bring on any of the other days. So this
fellow who we talked about who was lame on the first day
and then got better on the second day, on the first day
when the חיוב chiyuv was חל, chal, when the חיוב chiyuv came
down upon him,
he wasn't a בר חיובא. bar chiyuva. He wasn't somebody who could
be required to do this. Since he wasn't required to do this,
he doesn't have to pay it back in any sense. So, okay,
so that's not somebody who we would expect, therefore, who would need
to be חייב. chayav. So, we're back to our original question. הכל
לאתויי מאי? hakol l'atuyei mai? Who does this word, who does this
word include?
לאתויי סומא באחת מעיניו l'atuyei suma b'achat mei'einav to include somebody who
is blind in one eye.
ודלא כי האי תנא, u'd'la kehai tanna, but again, we're already saying
that we're holding according to a different position,
דתניא, detanya, than a ברייתא braita that says as follows. יוחנן בן
דהבאי אומר משום רבי יהודה סומא באחת מעיניו פטור מן הראייה. Yochanan
ben Dehavai omer mishum Rabbi Yehuda suma b'achat mei'einav patur min ha're'iyah.
So
Yochanan ben Dehavai who says that a person who's blind in one
eye doesn't have to bring a קרבן ראייה, korban re'iyah, he must
hold according to one of the earlier positions we saw, right? Because
so far, because he can't hold with the position that this person
is חייב. chayav. And he brings, what's the proof that, why does
he say that somebody who's blind in one eye can't bring a
קרבן ראייה? korban re'iyah? שנאמר יראה
יראה. shene'emar yeira'eh yeireh. רש״י Rashi says the word, it says שלוש
פעמים בשנה יראה כל זכורך את פני אדון ה׳. shalosh pe'amim bashana
yeira'eh kol zechurcha et pnei adon Hashem.
Three times a year all of your males shall
see/be seen by the master God. And that's exactly the point. It's
written יראה yeireh says רש״י, Rashi, you shall see, and it is
pronounced, we read it as יראה, yeira'eh, he shall be seen.
And we say that
כדרך שבא לראות כך בא ליראות. kederech sheba lirot kach ba lera'ot.
In the same way that he comes to see,
thus the same kind of person comes to be seen. מה לראות
בשתי עיניו? ma lirot bishtei einav? When you come to see something,
we normally, the normal standard of seeing is with two eyes. אף
ליראות בשתי עיניו. af lera'ot bishtei einav. Thus, to be seen you
also have to be able to see out of both eyes. And
immediately... somebody who's sensitive we have a whole of a
disabilities special disabilities training and so if you've been sensitized to this
your immediate thing to is your immediate response is to say wow
this is the the assumption of what is normal is fairly limited
here. That there yes many people see out of two eyes but
I'm not sure exactly what makes that normal. In any case
that's the position of יוחנן בן דהבאי. Yochanan ben Dehavai. So he
can't hold that position he has to either hold somebody who was
lame on one day and was able to walk on the next
day or he could even hold somebody who was half a slave
and half a free person.
So we could we could try to trace how does he hold
with regard to these other מחלוקות machlokot that we've seen considering that
he can't hold the position of the blind in one eye.
In any case we say oh we could go another direction. ואיבעית
אימא ve'iba'it eima actually we can leap- leapfrog this whole process that
we've just gone through and say לעולם כדאמרינן מעיקרא. le'olam kede'amrin me'ikara.
It's always as we said originally.
In other words half a slave half a half a free person.
ודקקשיא ליה הא דרבינא v'de'kakashala achda de'Ravina and the question that we
asked about רבינא Ravina because רבינא Ravina says somebody who's half a
slave and half a free person doesn't have to bring קרבן ראייה
korban re'iyah לא קשיא la kashya no problem. כאן במשנה ראשונה כאן
במשנה אחרונה. kan bemishna rishona kan bemishna achrona. There are actually two
משניות. mishnayot. The משנה mishna is compiled but people change their minds.
Things get changed even in the course of the משנה. mishna. And
therefore רבינא's Ravina position is according to the position of the משנה
ראשונה mishna rishona but later on it's he- he'd explain an early
משנה mishna but the actual משנה mishna that we hold להלכה l'halacha
is a different position. And now they're going to tell us what
it is. דתנן ditnan a משנה mishna in מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin
מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין עובד את רבו יום אחד
ואת עצמו יום אחד דברי בית הלל. mi shechetzyo eved vechetzyo ben
chorin oved et rabo yom echad ve'et atzmo yom echad divrei
Beit Hillel. Somebody who is a half a slave and half a
free person בית הלל Beit Hillel says he works part-time for his
master who still owns him he works one day and the next
day he does his own business. That's how he splits his time.
אמרו להם בית שמאי amru lahem Beit Shammai בית שמאי Beit Shammai
said to them
תיקנתם את רבו tikantem et rabo
you've solved the problem
you've made you've solved the problem of how is he going to
get his required labor in. את עצמו לא תיקנתם et atzmo lo
tikantem but you haven't solved his personal problems. There's a serious social
issue with somebody who is half a slave and half a free.
What's the problem? לישא שפחה אינו יכול lissa shifcha eino yachol he
can't get married to a maidservant because only slaves can get married
to female slaves to maidservants. בת חורין אינו יכול bat chorin eino
yachol בת חורין אינו יכול bat chorin eino yachol and he also
can't get married to a
free woman because free people are not allowed to marry slaves. So
this guy is stuck.
So we say ליבטל libatel maybe he should just refrain not get
married? והלא לא נברא העולם אלא לפריה ורביה vehalo lo nivra ha'olam
ela l'pirya v'rivya the whole world was created for the purpose of
propagation of the species for people and for people to to
propagate. שנאמר לא תהו בראה לשבת יצרה shene'emar lo tohu vera'ah lashevet
yetzarah he didn't create it for the purpose of chaos that is
to say God's not created the world for chaos but rather לשבת
lashevet in order to be settled. אלא
מפני תיקון
העולם ela
mipnei tikkun
ha'olam
because of תיקון העולם tikkun ha'olam solving the fixing things that are
sort of wrong in the world. And of course תיקון העולם tikkun
ha'olam has a very wide meaning today we kind of use it
as in as a idea of חסד. chesed. In מסכת גיטין Masechet
Gittin תיקון העולם tikkun ha'olam is a fairly narrow thing that has
to do with referring to legal issues that create perhaps social problems.
Charlie just one second.
So מפני תיקון העולם mipnei tikkun ha'olam כופין את רבו ועושה אותו
בן חורין kofin et rabo ve'oseh oto ben chorin the בית דין
Beit Din requires his master to actually free him entirely. If so
half of him is a slave we actually require the master to
to free him. וכותב לו שטר על חצי דמיו vechotev lo shtar
al chatzi damav and then the slave who has just been freed
now owes he writes a document saying I owe you this amount
of money which is the equivalent of half his slave price.
וחזרו בית הלל להורות כדברי בית שמאי vechezru Beit Hillel lehorot kedivrei
Beit Shammai and בית הלל Beit Hillel said oh you know... רבינא,
Ravina, when he said half a slave, half not a slave is
פטור patur from ראיה, reiyah, that was back when בית הלל Beis
Hillel thought that this, he was talking according to the position of
בית הלל Beis Hillel who said that this is actually a situation
which could continue indefinitely. Somebody could live their entire life or from
the time that they were that they became a slave until they
died as half a slave, half a free person. No problem, all
they would have to do is work one day for themselves, yeah,
work one day for their master. However,
once בית הלל Beis Hillel says, "Oh, you're right, maybe you solved
the master's problem, but the slave's problem still exists.
Okay, we'll go with your solution בית שמאי Beis Shammai that
we
should just..." Even in the case where ג Gimel gave it to
ד Daled to deliver and he delivered it in the very same
city as the husband was, why do we have this rule
of בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם? Bifnei nechtav u-bifnei nechtam? The point of
saying בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם Bifnei nechtav u-bifnei nechtam is in case
the husband comes and makes a ערעור, irur, a protest, saying this
is not my signature or this is not the witnesses' signature.
Therefore, since there are no people available to identify the signatures,
we had the שליח shaliach confirm it at the time he gave
the גט. get. That is only necessary when he is coming from
one province to another, or from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'Aretz to ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, or even within ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael from one
province to another. But if he stays within the same province,
then it is easy to find witnesses who will recognize the
signature and we don't need בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. Bifnei nechtav u-bifnei
nechtam. The number eight represents reaching beyond the physical world. We
see it in the ברית מילה Bris Milah because we want to
show that the connection of a child to הקדוש ברוך הוא
Hakadosh Baruch Hu is something that goes beyond the laws of
nature, למעלה מן הטבע. L'maala min ha'teva. We see it in חנוכה
Chanukah as well. There were many numbers we could have picked
but we pick eight because חנוכה Chanukah is the time where
we
want
to take the physical
world, the גשמיות Gashmius of the world,
and elevate it to
something more, into רוחניות. Ruchnius. And if you
look at the letters of the word שמונה, Shemonah, eight, they're the
same letters as the word נשמה, Neshamah, soul, and the word שמן,
Shemen, oil. Because the soul, the נשמה, Neshamah, is like the oil.
If you
put oil in water, it always rises to the top. It
doesn't mix. It's separate and it's higher. And that's what we're
trying to do. We're trying to reach that level of שמונה,
Shemonah, that level of being above nature, where our נשמה Neshamah is
what guides us and not just the natural world of שבע
Sheva around us. The גמרא Gemara says דוד David was a מקים
עול תשובה. Mekim Ol Teshuvah. He was the one who raised the
yoke of repentance. And that is why we say in תהילים,
Tehillim, מזמור לדוד. Mizmor Le-David. It was דוד'ס David's ability to take
responsibility for his actions, to say חטאתי, Chatati, I have sinned, and
to move forward. This is the power of דוד. David. This is
the power of תשובה. Teshuvah. He says over a beautiful piece from
the של"ה הקדוש. Shelah HaKodesh. The של"ה הקדוש Shelah HaKodesh says that
there's a reason why דוד המלך David HaMelech was the one chosen
to establish the concept of תשובה. Teshuvah. Because תשובה Teshuvah is not
just about saying sorry. תשובה Teshuvah is about recognizing that even after
a fall, even after a setback, one can still rise up
and be a מלך. Melech. A מלך Melech is not someone who
never fails. A מלך Melech is someone who knows how to deal
with failure. The של"ה Shelah says that דוד המלך David HaMelech had
this specific מדה midah of ענווה, anavah, humility. It was his ענווה
anavah that allowed him to do תשובה. Teshuvah. Because if you're not
humble, you can't admit you were wrong. And if you can't admit
you were wrong, you can't do תשובה. Teshuvah. He says further that
when דוד David said חטאתי לה', Chatati L'Hashem, I have sinned to
God, that was the moment he became the מלך Melech truly. Before
that, he was just a king by appointment. Now he was
a king by character. He says that the word תשובה Teshuvah has
the word שבת Shabbat in it. תשובה Teshuvah is תשוב ה', Tashuv
Hey, return the letter ה. hey. This is a very deep קבלה
Kabbalah concept. But simply put, it means returning to your source,
returning to הקדוש ברוך הוא. Hakadosh Barukh Hu. And that's why we
say that דוד המלך David HaMelech is related to the concept of
מלכות, Malchut, kingship. Because מלכות Malchut is the ability to take the
physical world and elevate it to the spiritual world, to take
a mistake and turn it into a מצוה. mitzvah. That's the power
of תשובה מאהבה, Teshuvah me-ahavah, repentance out of love, where the זדונות,
zedonot, the intentional sins, become זכויות, zechuyot, merits. This is what דוד
המלך David HaMelech taught us. מאימתי? Me'aimasai? מאימתי Me'aimasai means from when?
Why does the משנה Mishnah begin with a question of time? And
the שפת אמת Sefas Emes says that time is the definition of
change. Change and transitions. If a person was always in the
same state, if everything was always perfectly clear, if there was
no change in our lives, then there would be no room
for אמונה. emunah. אמונה emunah is the ability to connect to something
even when the circumstances around us are changing. Even when things
are not clear. Even when we're moving from light to darkness.
That's why the very first word of ש"ס Shas is מאימתי, Me'aimasai,
a question of time. Because the entire framework of our relationship
with השם, Hashem, the entire framework of our service of השם, Hashem,
is within the context of time. Within the context of a
world that is constantly changing. And our job is to find
the קביעות, kevi'us, the consistency, the connection to the eternal, within that
world of change. When the משנה Mishnah asks מאימתי קורין את שמע
בערבין, Me'aimasai korin es Shema be'aravin, when do we say שמע Shema
in the evening, it's telling us that specifically when the darkness
comes, that's when we have to say שמע ישראל השם אלקינו
השם אחד. Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad. We have to find
השם Hashem even in the change, even in the darkness. That's the
beginning of everything. That's the gateway to the entire תורה. Torah. It
says in the beginning of פרשת ויחי, Parshas Vayechi, ויחי יעקב בארץ
מצרים, Vayechi Yaakov b'eretz Mitzrayim, and Jacob lived in the land of
Egypt. And our חכמים Chachamim explain that the word ויחי Vayechi usually
means and he lived, but it can also mean and he
was revived. Because after all those years of suffering, יעקב Yaakov finally
found a sense of peace when he was reunited with יוסף.
Yosef. He saw that יוסף Yosef was still a צדיק, tzadik, he
saw that the שבטים Shevatim were all together, and he realized that
the legacy of אברהם Avraham and יצחק Yitzchak would continue. This is
the true meaning of living. It is not just about existence,
it is about seeing our values and our faith being passed
down to the next generation. And this is why יעקב Yaakov called
his children together before he passed away. He wanted to give
them the ברכות berachos that would give them the strength to survive
the גלות. Galus. He knew that the only way they would stay
strong is if they stayed connected to their שורש, shoresh, to their
roots. And this is the message for all of us as
we finish ספר בראשית. Sefer Bereishis. We have to be חזק חזק
ונתחזק. Chazak chazak v'nis-chazek. We have to strengthen ourselves and each other
in our אמונה emunah and our commitment
to
תורה.
Torah.
Because
that
is
what
keeps
us
alive
as
a
nation,
no
matter
where
we
are
or
what
challenges
we
face.